Kiana: Have a question.
- How many holes—
Haz: (interrupts) Yes.
Kiana: ... does a woman have from the waist down?
Haz: Two.
Kiana: Okay, so what are those holes used for?
Haz: A lot of things— (unsure)
(Kiana laughs)
What do you mean?
What are you ask—
- Yeah, it's just a general, like—
An easy, like, biological question.
What is ...
What are those two holes used for?
- I mean, like, bathroom-wise?
- Yes.
- Poop and pee?
- (laughs) Poop and pee.
- And then where's the ...
- Yeah?
- Where's the sex one, dude?
- The pee one?
(Kiana glees and claps)
Okay? (confused)
(Kiana giggles)
- Oh my God
- What's the joke?
- That's so cute.
That's so fucking cute, dude.
It's like, dude ...
You really never had a woman ... like ...
- What is going on?
What, you pee from your butt?