It's May, with a lot of snow in the mountains.
I will explore.
With me, I have Tor Olsen and Nina.
We each have our dogs.
We'll go south on the Swedish side,
but in the wild mountains.
We do not know where we'll end up,
and it's a wonderful plan to have.
-Is it time to camp?
-Yes, now is the time for it.
Now to the fishing,
but there's something we should do first.
-You are missing something in my head, Tor.
-Hair?
I'm not referring to it.
-You are rude!
I thought that I'd wear my cap with
"Northern Scandinavia 365" on it.
-Such a cap would be glorious gift.
-Thank you.
It suits me like a shot. Good!
("FISH THIEF")
I could not help myself.
Holy Father!
But I have no fishing license card!
We arranged for licenses for Tor, -
- so now he can fish on
with a clear conscience.
It was small then.
Then I lost it, great.
Soon there will be coffee.
It's the third morning,
and snow pounded the tent.
Today, the weather is worse.
No doubt.
Is there any life down at Olsen?
There something wrong at Tor's tent.
I hope it's serious.
What were the problems with the tent?
It looked like you fell.
I was freaking dizzy
and fell on my ass.
I do not know what it is or anything,
So I choose to cancel my trip.
I will go down and get it checked.
It need not be serious -
- but there is not much chance to run
dogs when I'm so dizzy.
We've done about 10 or 12 tours together.
It's the first time I've seen you sick.
We must take it seriously.
We fear
that Tor has heart problems.
Fortunately, we're only two kilometers
away from an emergency phone.
It's Lars Monsen.
Do you hear me?
He fell over.
He was dizzy and just fell apart.
He has had problems with his heart,
so it could be the heart.
We need you to pick him up.
Is it a helicopter or snowmobile?
-Can you walk over to the helicopter?
-I have gone a bit back and forth.
So we'll go to Narvik hospital
where they'll examine you properly.
It's sad. Now we turn around,
and Thor's not here anymore.
It's really sad. Tor had
rejoiced, and it was his holiday.
He said it to me
while you called for help, -
- that this was his holiday
and the annual high point.
When you get out this far,
it's right to call for help.
Don't take any chances. It's sour
at the moment, but one gets over it.
We shall go on more trips.
I can't get rid Olsen so easily.
All is well with Tor.
He is well at home.
An ear injury was detected,
and it affected the balance.
Thanks to the Norwegian Air Ambulance
for the great help.
It's incredible
that one can get help so quickly.
We got the dogs down from the mountain,
and Foss and I continued alone.
We'll go south on the Swedish side
of the border towards Sitasjaure.
So we take one day at a time.
It was a tough march,
but now we are over the watershed.
We have gone up from Alesjaure.
There is no fishing.
Closer to the Norwegian border, there are several
waterways, but it's first in the morning.
Foss and his owner are very tired.
Six hours of hard work in the hills.
So we fire up the primus
and enjoy us some heat.
I found one snow-free moraine ridge.
We are up at almost 1000 meters.
Today is a day of rest. It's
windy and snowy towards the Norwegian border.
No need to fight the weather.
I've had a lot of bad weather the
first week, but the mountain is rough.
Nothing needs to happen.
One can be a bit quiet.
Fire up the Primus, write
and take a little walk -
- around the small moraine mound
I have camped at.
Enjoy the taste of our surrounding
tent. Otherwise, it's full winter.
I'll wait of course for
the fine weather to strike.
Eternal optimist, always.
Now the other team has arrived.
Blue sky, fighting the weather in the mountains.
Passing my old jig holes,
I stop and use them.
The important thing is to get food.
Now I am at Tjarvejaure.
Spring is wonderful in the mountains, but
summer is on its way into the lowlands.
It makes me restless.
It's tempting to fish.
It's illegal to fish here,
and reindeer are calving now.
So I do plan B.
I'll go to the East.
Nina can bring the equipment and a canoe.
I can go on
summer's first adventure.
It's 25 May, and the clock is at 23.30.
The sun has just gone down,
and in three hours it's back.
Now it's long, bright days in the north.
It was delicious real campfire coffee.
(learn to properly light a fire at nrk.no/monsen)
It's strange to think
of winter now.
No more dog-sledding,
ski, sled and freezing.
Now it's full summer.
Total opposite of the dark period.
Outdoor activity offers perspectives
when you are out all year -
- and experience all the shifts,
feel it in the body.
Then set the proper price for this.
Sleeping under the open sky
in a half poor sleeping bag.
The dog lies on the ground.
Most are single in the summer.
If one then accept
some smoke in one's eyes.
When it's so bright at night,
it's good with anything over the eyes.
As usual I
tend to be a little like that.
Good night, Foss.
What I should do now,
is to fish down Big Luleälv.
I'm going to Muddus National Park,
I am very curious about it.
Are you ready, Foss?
He has never been in a canoe before.
But he has learned
to carry the pack like a god.
He began to draw a sledge in winter
and draws as a god.
Now you should just
sit in the canoe as a god.
Let's try, Foss.
Such o clever puppy!
Such a good boy!
Lie still.
There you go.
Good boy!
Good boy, you are!
It turned out great.
Here, it was fine. Here I can lie,
and then you can lie on the side.
Views of the river
and a little shelter from the wind. A nice place.
He smells something. It can be
reindeer, and it can be a bear.
It's nice to have a dog,
especially in bear country, like here.
Keeping my eye on him,
I'll always have a little notice.
As I do not sleep deeply.
But now it's summer and bright
and difficult to sleep deeply.
Now the fishing.
Wonderful! This year's first fishing pole,
and it there will be more.
I tethered Foss up along the river
and went to fish a little.
Some rustling in the grass behind me,
and damned if it wasn't snakes.
It's not often
one sees them so far north.
It's fascinating.
Im here with short sneakers
and feel a little naked on the ankles.
It's good Foss is bound in the woods.
I wonder if this is a pairing.
In this case, it's a rare sight.
Oi, oi, oi ...
Here we come paddling, -
- and damned if it's not
a dead moose on the beach.
Had this moose been partially eaten,
I would have hesitated to go into the area, -
- since there could be bear.
They can defend a moose cadaver as well,
so I have to hang back a bit.
It's not eaten by the bear yet.
It's just a matter of time
before Bamsefar discovers the carcass.
It's hard to say
what it died of. It's full.
It's good to see these things too.
Although it's a dead animal,
it's a natural sight.
In the wilderness you will find animals
who have suffered a natural death -
- as has this one.
Are you going to be with us
moose hunting in the fall?
I've been curious
about Muddus for years.
Virgin forests, bird life, wildlife ...
It's very rich.
Unfortunately, dogs are not allowed.
Foss must stay at home then.
Foss is so used to tour living
that he knows that I'll come back.
We started the training
in Pasvik.
Now there's excitement in my stomach,
for I know that there are bears here.
The path is covered
from the start.
It's a typical Swedish thing.
It's pleasant to walk on Kloppene.
And it saves nature the wear and tear,
no doubt about it.
After a couple of hours
I arrived at Muddus-fall.
A few meters away I see the falls.
I must have have heard them far away.
Imagine being trout in free fall
down there. It must tickle the eggs!
Half of Muddus is virgin forest,
and half is wetland.
You feel like you're all alone,
especially now in the early summer.
The mood is now
indescribably beautiful.
The terrain in Muddus is easily passed,
aside from the marshes.
It's wonderful at this time.
It's the last day of May,
and spring is on the wane.
It seethes with life in the forest.
It's so hot during the day
I travel at night.
The atmosphere is fantastically fine.
Chances rise for
encounters with wild animals.
Yes! I saw a Muddus-bear.
I had not imagined.
It's one ten at night.
Now it's out walking.
The sun rests only in the middle of the day.
It was a real journey out, then!
It was a brilliant end of a
detour to Muddus National Park.
Here I shall return.
Such things are fun, especially here.
This is typical bear forest.
It's clear there are bears here.
When their reaction is like that,
it's just fun.
People have little to fear,
for that meeting was typical.
Most bears are afraid.
Wow, I've seen a bear.
It's fun. Fun!
Thank you for that,
you showed up for a few seconds.
It was not bad, this.
Good size for it.
This, then?
It sat there, also.
It's clumsy with two rods
at the same time, but I ask the about it.
There are two pike.
Oi, oi, oi!
It was close. Vanished like smoke.
The fish are in the boat
with wobblers in the mouth.
Oi, oi, oi ...
It was noon today, too.
Such a good boy!
This is a great time for tours.
Summer parties seized.
It becomes more and more lively.
Birds sing, the fish bite ...
The idea of swinging a fishing rod every day
of the summer is a fantastic delight.
Now we are talking fish.
Lake perch, that is.
This is a kick in the head. Four or five
provide an excellent dinner.
Number two.
Number three.
They are not fighting much,
since the food is potato chips
Number four.
It's not mashed potatoes for dinner tonight.
(next week)
Look at it, then!
There was lots of gold.
Is it possible
to see the beautiful nugget?
(English subtitles: Lex Ein)
(lexein-subs at yahoo dot com)
Sun Dec 06 2009 00:13:12