2. December. I find myself
in Jokkmokk in northern Sweden.
Dark Age has started. We have prepared
equipment for 40 days in the field.
We want to have Christmas & New Year's
going out and return when the sun returns.
Foss, come on!  Here!
Come on!
I have a suspicion
that there will be a lot of dog training.
He will manage this. 50 kilograms in the sled
is nothing when well fed.
Such a good boy!
It takes time to get ready
with household duties.
Three hours, from when I
started digging the clay pit.
Setting the tarp, cutting wood for
the whole evening and the next morning.
This is no lazy man's life.
I get ready for the
morning fire in the evening.
When I cut enough, I'll prepare
them and put them in the bag -
- or under the tarp. Then
I just reach out my hand, -
- stoke the fire and get
a pleasant start to the day.
When you go on tour in the dark period,
You're affected by lack of daylight.
Everything requires more energy.
It's important to cooperate with nature.
Trust me well, the reward is
great. The light is fantastic.
I look forward to arriving at
Sarekfjellene to re-sight the sun.
This is no different than what I
did when I was 17-18 years old.
In the northern forest, the Krokskogen.
When we did this on weekends.
Lying under open sky
or with just a tablecloth over us.
As if time stood still.
The difference is, of course,
the wilderness up here is huge.
There is an enormous amount of untouched forest.
Here you can go in for weeks alone.
It's dimly lit. The clock is at 12,
but lighter it will not get.
We must sieze the day, Foss.
There can be 30-50 cm of snow
in the course of one day.
So we need to move us as we can.
Would rather be quiet for a few days.
What's this?
It's not often that you see that.
Orrhane, black grouse. Here one of
nature's own hunters have been busy.
A bird carcass tends not to remain
long. A fox probably got it.
What do you think? Don't you want it?
You can gnaw on it tonight.
You'd rather be alone
when you eat.
It's advantageous to pack up a sled.
We are self-sufficient for the whole trip.
I've included lots of bread,
bacon, coffee and many other luxuries.
Nevertheless, I hope
to be able to outwit a fish.
There is little fuss to get the
food itself.
It's best to use live bait.
I try to keep it alive in the field.
In my slipper. Everything wild
goes in the slippers.
They're not completely frozen stiff.
There's actually a sign of life yet.
No.
Mark one has been hanging in peace.
I see the fish well.
It's there, certainly a nice fish.
But he scoffs at the sport fishermen
on the ice trying to fool it.
Fish are like humans.
They are affected by the lack of light.
So they wait for a sufficiently
brighter, warmer season.
I will be at this camp two or three days.
It's so nice here.
Now the cold has settled
like a lid over the landscape.
Almost no life to hear.
An occasional owl calls out.
There are of course tracks
of reindeer, hares and stuff.
Nature has been in here.
It's incredibly large to be
part of.
With the cold, short days, everything
that moves is in low gear in December -
- I would not put right
a great value on those moments -
- when it's easy in the summer.
That's only six months away.
And before that there's the spring, also.
Shall we proceed?
There are three days left for Christmas.
Think I'll push on a bit -
- to find a nice Christmas camp.
Incredible changes here.
As if someone turned on a switch,
it was 30 degrees in a snap.
For a day since it was
27-28 minus, now it's two plus.
It has begun to blow,
and the snow just plummets from the trees.
Bombarding everything on the ground.
The dog jumps, scared around here.
I had to lower the liner
and bear down better.
Now we're well sheltered under the cloth.
Sleeping to the sound of the wind that roars
in the treetops, is incredibly delicious.
Now it's 9.30, but as usual it will be
half an hour until there's good daylight.
Now I sit in a sleeping bag
and check out the terrain, -
- The green woods which
yesterday were chalk white.
Now I sit here in the fresh
spring wind and enjoy my coffee.
In December.
This is not normal, this here.
What, out and about solo?
Two days before Christmas?
Been sacked by Santa Claus? Rumors
yesterday that he has shifted to using dogs.
-Are there any _good_ children here?
-At least one.
Take this, you. Now I travel on.
I think, for the rest I go.
-This year's first gingerbread.
-Cohabitation: Nina and the dogs are in place.
We have it so peaceful, just as we wish.
Now, Christmas Eve parties.
You're awesome.
May I hang the star?
This is really good.
-Merry Christmas.
-In the same way.
Think this is Christmas number
16 or 17 for me out there.
This is the perfect way to celebrate
that we are moving towards brighter days.
The feeling is insanely lovely.
Now there are only a few weeks -
- and then one senses how the longer
days win back the soul.
Good to be back in the tent.
Have not used it since Pasvik.
When Nina and the dogs said goodbye,
she took with her cloth, ax and saw.
These I swapped out
for the tent and Primus stove.
I have a very sheltered home again.
One is more exposed to wind under the cloth.
But I will miss having a bonfire.
It's mildly pleasant, with a primus.
But this is the safest option.
For now I'm in high hilly terrain.
Here I'm much more vulnerable
to storms and bad weather.
May as well dig up New Year's frame.
What are the arrangements for chicken?
Now at 12 it's midnight.
You have a happy New Year!
Thanks, the same as you said.
And so we celebrate.
Hip, hurray in the mountains!
Much better than rockets
which smell and make noise.
It's in honor of you,
because you are such a fine companion.
So I say very quickly:
Thank you for this year.
Cheers, Foss.
T'Was the celebration.
Northern Sweden has many sled team leaders.
I follow the best known, -
- Kungsleden.
He runs from Hemavan to Abisko.
Foss has become much better at drawing the sled
and not losing sled track markings.
This is valuable if you decide to follow
tracks leading into in the mountains.
I'm overtaking the sled when Foss had
gone ahead with it for about an hour.
It applies to them
while the game is good.
If it's heavy and tiring
mentally, he loses the desire.
Now he draws only in the group.
That's where he really belongs.
Well, we came across the water
before it got dark.
There's not much life.
Is it open, so one night in a house.
There is luxury in the mountains.
You were so good today!
Are you so fond of scratching your back?
Should not be so long calm before
know minus the ranks under his clothes.
Here, it was locked.
Oh no. It's this door.
In Sweden, there are often
several lodges in one place.
Then they lock everything but
one room. Here it's open enough.
Wood stove. That's the most important.
And four logs on.
Tonight it's the mattress.
Sitojaurestugan belongs to the Swedish
Tourist association and is open to all.
As a member, I pay $100 per night.
A little more expensive for non-members.
Weird stuff.
Must be a kløyveredskap.         (?!)
Swedish patent?
How does one do this, then?
There will be a little noise here, buddy.
You can do this til tomorrow morning.
... 26, 27, 28, 29 ...
Think I prefer the old way.
Dark Age creeps into your soul.
You go down to low gear.
Some thrive in a curious way, but
you go without smiling for a long time.
Who does it bothers, anyway?
Being here, feel the atmosphere,
get a reminder -
- that we humans are like animals ...
They remain calm now.
They don't have the same activity
as when the light comes to our nights.
But until nature shows upk
with more daylight, I'll sleep a lot.
I have thought to do that now,
though it's only half past seven.
Hopefully I'll wake up
when daylight comes, the 9-9.30 time.
We will be, over the watershed,
at almost 800 meters altitude.
It's not difficult to find.
Kungsleden is fairly straightforward.
Weatherproof day. Lying quietly,
relax, write a little, drink coffee.
(learn to repair a tent at nrk.no/monsen)
One gale, and the -3.4 degrees
yesterday becomes -22 degrees.
It's clear, fine weather.
Probably I will see the sun today.
Wonderful to see the sun shine
on the mountain tops again.
What a trip this has been. Being
out through the dark times ...
Enjoyable moments. Seeing see the sun again,
knowing that every day is a little brighter.
In contrast to the start of
December, spring is much closer now.
Before I head off to the lowlands,
I will give the fish a last attempt.
(next week)
Must work as a whole to hang on.
(English subtitles: Lex Ein)
(lexein-subs at yahoo dot com)
Sat Dec 05 2009 09:02:55