It's now 19 January.
It's two months until the
Finnmarksløpet dogsled  race starts.
Now I am on the
first real training ride.
I started with 16 dogs.
And I went straight into the snow,
so now I'm in a tricky little spot.
16 insane sled dogs.
Ever idiots!
I lie
with my bone inside the brake.
It can actually break
if they get themselves going now.
I gotta get up
and put away the camera.
I find myself in Alta.
Soon we'll see the start of Europe's
toughest race for mushers.
I compete
with 14 highly trained dogs.
My girlfriend, Nina, has trained them
for 5000 kilometers since August.
Now Nina has done that job.
The rest is up to me.
All who are running
the long Finnmarksløpet race, -
- must have at least two "handlers".
A handler is a helping person.
I have three.
Nina.
Hans Christian Ørjestad the chauffeur.
And Frode Galaaen. His job
is to keep me in good spirits.
Now it's again only 1000 kilometers.
We'll talk at the end of next week.
You must come up with
some hints along the way!
Now we are handling lots of stuff, so
you get to eat at check points.
-Coffee, bananas ...
And the latest Donald magazine.
There was so much bacon to choose from.
I bought this "Forest Bacon".
I looked for "Mountains & Vistas"
bacon, but they didn't have any.
Two or three minutes to go.
The pressure cooker is lit now.
There is a transition
to come from the tour life -
- and into a competitive situation.
But I want to try something new.
Tour- and expedition- life
are a safe venue for me.
It's not a competitive situation.
This feeling I like.
There are five seconds til start!
Bye!
Finnmarksløpet
is 1047 kilometer long.
This corresponds to the distance
from Oslo-Narvik as the crow flies.
The run has twelve checkpoints
where all participants must stop.
A checkpoint is a place
where the dogs can rest and get care.
The competition runs for one week.
First person to cross the
finish line at Alta, wins.
Hi, Thomas!
-Hey, Lars!
-You're surging past!
-Do it in the beginning.
Long Distance Mushing
is a sport.
Many of those who compete
have been doing this for decades.
My goal is ambitious.
I hope to finish in the top ten.
To others, I say "top 20".
It's to take away some pressure.
When one is overtaken,
one brakes to let the other pass.
You are on the trip, Lars?
It was Ralph Johannesen,
one of my favorites.
He sailed past in a sitting position.
Familiar style.
We'll give him a trip, we shall!
There are two areas where
I lack experience.
Firstly, it's Nina
who has trained the dogs, -
- so my contact
with dogs is not tops.
Second is the checkpoint procedures.
Most can do
their checkpoint procedures in 25 minutes.
While I'll
fumble around for perhaps an hour.
Thus losing rest
for the dogs and I.
This is a typical beginner mistake.
I forgot to bring straw.
Similar to sleep in a barn.
We can decide ourselves
how long to stay at a checkpoint.
How long should one sleep? How far
should one go to exert themselves?
I'm not going to lie here
too long. One and a half hours.
I do not think
many are resting so btiefly.
I forgot to sign myself out.
No sport has as much wilderness
in it as long-distance mushing.
That's what draws me
to this sport.
Here you can experience forests,
mountains, streams, wildlife, birdlife -
- while competing.
It's very fascinating!
Room Service!
Open the door, please!
The plan is that you should run nicely
110 kilometers to Skippagurra.
Quiet.
You have fifteen minutes to eat,
and then you have to work as a whole.
You will be out at 12.37.
I spent five hours and thirteen
minutes at this checkpoint.
The dogs are rested.
I must myself be content with
a half hour's sleep.
Great to run in daylight, guys!
It's nice here!
And it's delicious
to get a track with a decent base.
A dream to see you right now.
But it's far.
110 kilometers to Skippagurra.
Into Skippagurra
I lie in ninth place.
But it's early in the race.
Behind me are
very many good riders.
They will increase the pace,
going as fast!
The dogs are the focus. Every one
is checked thoroughly by veterinarians.
If they have an injury,
they are taken out of the race.
A run can be disqualified
for poor dog care.
No dehydration.
That's good.
The veterinarian said in fact these
are the nicest dogs she had seen -
- at this checkpoint.
It's a compliment.
Especially to Nina, who has had
primary responsibility for the dogs.
310 km, nearly a third of the race,
is done.
Checkpoint routines
are much better now.
So I get
one and a half hours of shuteye.
Good morning, sunshine!
Have you any appetite?
-I ate one solid meal.
-That was a long time ago.
Now we have lit the primus
with a single match.
Eat and enjoy! You have twelve minutes
until you are out there.
-Bring what's there.
-We are relentless!
Now at five ten. I
will actually turn out at six.
But the dogs are fit. I cut
rest here by half an hour.
Where is it that
I turn to Neiden now?
Just straight ahead?
Shouldn't it
be sub-zero temperatures here?
-How long will
you be here?
-Is it normal to say that?
-We want to know.
Isn't it a secret?
There are more than three hours.
All drivers must have
rest for 16 hours.
One can choose
the checkpoints one does it at.
We chose Neiden.
Five hours of sleep before I go..
isn't it grand!
Sixteen hours
over about twenty minutes.
It has become colder. Fortunately.
We had trouble going yesterday.
Then it was mild.
Now it's hard, fine tracks, but
it's a bit milder throughout the day.
Most people took their 16-hours
rest at Skippagurra or Neiden.
It's only afterwards -
- that we know
our standings.
As I leave Neiden,
I'm in the top ten.
I'm very pleased!
Now we have to run for nearly seven hours.
This is so nagging.
It's very rhythm of the team.
We have at maximum a few hours left
with this pace.
Now I will speak as little as possible and
just work. I've kicked the whole time.
Now we hang
back on the next driver in front of us.
Now I'll let him see us,
and I'll take a break.
Now he saw me.
But it's dangerous
to be too high in position.
It's a game.
It's easy
to get one in the face in return.
Suddenly stopping the dogs, -
- and then it's you he drives by
waving you over.
Just be a little humble.
This goes like a greased pig!
You just go and go and do the job.
Now we've run 525 kilometerss.
Over half way.
We have taken our 16-hour break.
The stated objective now
is to be among the twenty best.
It's not quite true.
My goal is "top 10".
Right now it looks very good.
Tactics is a very important word
in long-distance mushing.
It makes it so fascinating.
If I move down to the dogs,
the other drivers will know it.
Frode came up with smart suggestion:
I'm going to dress like him,
fool my way past the team -
- and disappear into the darkness.
It seems that
tactic worked.
I leave Kirkenes
and am still among the top ten.
At the same time I start
to notice fatique.
And it's due to
very little sleep.
Eleven hours in four days.
Now I'm fairly tired.
They say it's worse in the morning,
and it's true.
Now we have run
in six and a half hours from Kirkenes.
Come on!
Spark Inga has started zombie-kicking.
The legs are moving,
but not always in the right direction.
10:35 it says there.
Ok, when I run, guys.
Bet that there
is a little speed in the slot.
It seems that
I left Neiden -
- simultaneously with another
not unknown man.
Are you going to leave now, Roger?
Yes, I will try to get
in front of him before Lars Monsen.
It's not difficult.
If there is anyone who deserves
title Mr. Finnmarksløpet, -
- it's Roger Dahl.
He has completed twenty times,
stood on the podium eight times -
- and won twice.
Only once has he broken down.
Then he drove with a chauffeur.
If you manage to hang with Roger,
you are guaranteed a good position.
But he does not wait.
We have to work as a whole
to hang on.
All this goes beyond all expectations.
There is really good punch in the team.
We hang on with Roger!
There, we are actually!
It's incredibly cozy
when approaching a checkpoint.
They set up lights and signs.
I feel that we are welcome.
People appreciate
this competition.
It's awesome!
Come on!
Welcome!
It was fun to run with Roger here.
But what's Roger doing now?
How long will he rest?
Will he push off again?
Wonder if he
just ran off in the twilight?
As I lay asleep.
It could not lure me away.
Yes, now it's just Monsen
we must compete against.
-Come on!
-Good luck!
I have
one and a half hours of sleep.
I am running out right in
front of Roger.
This turns quickly. An hour ago
I was behind Roger Dahl in a fine drive.
Now it's all out.
Now we'll soon be on, guys.
The dogs are very well trained.
This is a psychological reaction.
It could be because I have
for poor contact with them.
I have not been on the sled enough.
I must try to get them going again.
It's not far to Sirbma.
Come on!
It took ten minutes.
Good girl! Come on!
Come on, Teddy! Good boy!
I can not talk too much.
Must concentrate on these now.
I got them going again.
Will see if it holds all the way down.
Long Distance Mushing
has ups and downs.
Seven hours of rest is
having a good effect -
- and we kept good pace
in two stages too.
But then we had a real surprise.
Now there are only 60 km left of
the race, and here they suddenly stopped.
I can only wait.
And so they have to find out when
they are inspired to move their legs.
Break we do not.
We shall finish.
I know Tore Bergby have won.
Roger Dahl running probably
into an eighth.
And for me it's about getting
to goals, to reach the banquet.
Now we go to Alta.
Are you ready? Ok!
Ok! Come on!
You are an old traveler.
You have run very far.
A short jog is just for fun.
So nice!
This looks good.
You could run!
Come on!
Are you ready? Ok! Come on!
Good boy!
How nice! Here goes away!
There is a positive experience
To see the attitude people have.
Although there is a competition,
they help each other out.
Ok! Yes!
But it means
I arrive at the banquet.
I'll be in goal at No. 25
More than a day
off the best drivers.
It was not exactly what I had
planned, but I have learned a lot.
-Congratulations!
-Thanks!
I have a little gift for you.
You're a tough man.
Colleagues have come to visit.
Thank you, Frode.
One thing is for sure:
To run the Finnmarksløpet
is a monumental experience of nature.
And such great fun -
- I guarantee
I will compete again.
(next week)
Now we can start moving.
(English subtitles: Lex Ein)
(subs.hopto.org)
Sun Dec 06 2009 01:10:13 mmi-km