There is my
first fish from Lake Inari.
I am excited to see
what kind of fish this is.
It was char, Foss.
Finland is
a paradise for canoers.
"The thousand lakes" has
more than 60,000 lakes.
Inari is the third largest.
I'll paddle a week to Lake Inari,
and on to Vatsari.
It's
exciting wilderness for Norwegians.
From there I'll go over the Norwegian border,
to Munk down river and into the Arctic Ocean.
Now let's enjoy ourselves.
30 days to the end, Foss.
Here we camp.
Does it pass?
30 meters long
and between 5 and 20 meters wide.
It's nice to camp on an island.
I can forget Foss
without worrying that he's gone.
He doesn't like to swim.
But I carry the canoe well on land.
The road's 20 km up the waterway.
The canoe won't operate that way.
In a canoe I can
take with me a lot of luxury.
Such as a gas burner.
And I have the big model.
Then Foss and I can spread out.
One appreciates having plenty of space.
Also I have this.
A habit I brought with me.
It's a bit unusual to carry
around, especially for a 45-year-old.
But it's great luxury
to only be able to ...
... stretch out on a child mattress.
There are issues, there!
There you go.
This can be the first kilogram
over the border on this trip.
Wonderful!
It's not a kilo, but ... 700.
Wonderful trout!
There's some fight left in it.
Now it's starting to run down.
Look at this beautiful trout!
It's dinner today, Foss.
It weighs 1.2 kg.
Now I stand facing a classic choice
canoers face on the Great Lakes.
I'm going over there.
It's a mile of open water.
I can hit waves that have been
moving from the south for seven miles.
The waves can be large even if
I don't see foam tops from here.
I can get them from the side, and
they can ripple into the boat.
One may want
to wait until evening.
Then, waves are smaller as a rule.
But you can also put on the skirt.
This prevents the waves
and the water lapping into the canoe.
We are now across.
There's even a sandy beach.
I think there's a campground here.
There, we slipped nicely and neatly
into calmer waters.
The week on Lake Inari has
been excellent.
Not least, we finish with
water that's completely calm.
Beautiful paddle over. But there's something
that lures behind the hill down there.
It's only a few kilometers away.
There ends Lake Inari in the north.
I''ll go
into the Vatsari wilderness area.
Finns refer to it as the most
inaccessible wilderness of Finland.
Such things are tempting for me.
I have to go in there.
With the canoe and the dog and everything.
In a countercurrent to begin with.
The alternative is to carry,
but it's usually five twists.
This goes much faster.
It does not require more energy -
- if you do it steadily
and are careful where you go.
Now only small
currents again, so we are up there.
There's a nice size to it.
It smells of kilogram fish.
The question: just what kind?
These are pike.
Another, much larger pike
follows the one on the hook.
We'll release it into the water
hoping that we get something else.
Trout and char, they'll work.
Parr's good, too.
We have begun to be picky.
Oh, good boy!
The first time you've crossed alone.
It's quite important
that he dares to do it.
Oh, good boy!
You were so good, Foss.
It turned out well, there.
When the dog can cross the river,
I can stop worrying about it -
- when there are many narrow passages
with drawing the canoe and paddling.
Then it's better that
the dog runs along the shore.
We will wade up here too.
But sometimes I fish the pools
before stomping around in them, -
- and it pays off now. This is a
wonderful trout we must get on board.
No, it escaped!
You went out there and swim back now?
Clearly a  Canada-dog, this.
It was great to paddle on Lake Inari,
but once I am here, -
- comes the real wilderness feeling.
Waves alone, no marked trails,
no roads, no cars, no people.
Only the dog, the canoe and I
and a river we fish for dinner in.
Like this.
There are lots of them.
No!
Is it gone now?
I had just turned up the tent.
Here's something I'm glad I have now,
though I'm an old bonfirer, -
- and that's the gas appliance.
The terrain of scree
is typical of Vatsari.
The area is 1550 square kilometers.
This is bigger
than Børgefjell National Park.
Boulders make it difficult
to travel here on foot.
It's considerably easier with the canoe,
although I have to leave it downstream.
If one is walking, one must
have strong ankles and sturdy footwear.
You must be accustomed to wild life.
I have come far up the river,
it's easy to see.
The main river's
one and a half feet wide.
Then it becomes a lot of scree,
a disappearing stream.
It gets narrower and narrower.
Here we must begin to bear.
One should inspect the canoe sometimes
to see if there's a hole somewhere.
Here are a few leaks
which must be sealed.
(learn to pack a canoe at nrk.no/monsen)
Wonderful!
Now I come to Surnujärvi.
I've had the greatest fishing trip.
I have taken enough.
I need to paddle to shore.
It vanished.
Like smoke.
It was huge, I mean.
I just saw a giant swirl -
- then it spun with its tail
and said goodbye.
It may have been
between three and five kilograms.
Yes, yes.
That's it.
Just grit your teeth.
I've got dinner today,
but I was sad.
Now we spent an hour
for one kilometer as the crow flies.
Huge are the fish in the lake.
Have not had coffee before a fish bites.
Yesterday it was completely dead.
Typical char behavior.
It seemed totally totally dead.
Oi, it's trout.
Wonderful trout.
Oi, oi, oi, for a nice fish!
It jumped when it saw you, Foss.
Have you ever seen!
And so beautiful.
It's the most picturesque trout
I've ever had.
One and a half kilo, at least.
Managed to shoulder a nice fish!
Look at it, then!
It's 1.7kg. A late Saturday night
might sneak it over 2 also.
It's useless to fish and just
stand there, really use the rod.
When it's so quiet on the water,
this is a good solution.
A float with a hole clean through.
No lead, only worms.
When the fish snatches a worm,
there's no resistance.
The leader runs through the float.
Had it been solid lead shot here, -
- the big fish will
become suspicious.
Where you can experience things this big
in a small pond?
It takes me five minutes
to walk around it.
There are signs
of pristine wilderness.
That's where a few people
and fish can live in peace.
That's where it's full.
It's a beautiful delicacy, -
- if only there were toast.
A wonderful diversion. There are
different delicacies than mackerel in tomato.
Pleasant visit in the morning,
litttle løvskrika.
It has a nose for food.
Especially for grayling
I've seen it eat.
Fly away with a belly full.
Fish waste can be spread in the trees
and bushes around the camp.
It's good food sense.
Go ahead, it's to you.
Now you need to eat.
An angry mink.
It has no retreat
and feels trapped.
It's angry, so we have to watch it.
The biting's guaranteed.
We'll let him alone, Foss.
Oh, good boy!
I have carried the canoe
down to Porojaure.
I'm on the river
which is 'Munk' river on the Norwegian side.
'Uutuanjoki' in Finnish.
Here we begin to get more water.
It's not entirely pure in style,
but we come down.
About five days til this trip's over.
And the whole project is over.
I try not to think about it,
but enjoy the moment while I have it.
I have already
taken a kilo pike.
Got Foss' name on that one,
and "Lars" on this.
Now you must try to approach your country.
It still has power.
This I will have up.
Come on, then!
Shall we try?
Won't you do it?
There's space here.
Come on.
I have driven it for ten minutes.
Dinner!
Beautiful fish, etc.
Good boy!
Gone well, but home's the best.
It's wonderful to be in Norway again.
Now it's autumn again. I've
been through the four seasons.
From the autumn of last year, with the first
snow, and ever shorter days, -
- I knew I would
be on tour throughout the winter.
Then came spring.
I was there when the ice broke up.
I was there
when the birds began to chirp.
It gives pleasure to see the changing face
of nature through all the seasons.
I am enormously grateful
to have experienced all this.
Not least that I have
experienced it at home in Scandinavia.
One need not go to Alaska or
Canada to experience pristine wilderness.
One gets the feeling
of being completely alone in solitude -
- and the silence of the woods
and the mountains we have here at home.
It's about going after the dream
and taking that step fully.
All the trips I have undertaken,
make it very clear.
One must decide
and make it known in good time.
Most people are prevented
by job and family.
The civilized carousel
we know all too well.
But announce it two years in advance to
family, employer and yourself.
Start planning.
Say that in August in two years
are you on an expedition in the wild.
I get paid for our toil!
We show off the trophy.
Can I hold it?   -Okay, thanks! Bye!
It was a wolf!
Got fired by Santa Claus?
Any good children here?  -Yes, one...
The cold has settled like a lid over the landscape.
Hip, hurray in the mountains!
Thank you for showing up.
(English subtitles: Lex Ein)
(lexein-subs at yahoo dot com)
Sun Dec 06 2009 01:18:04 mmi-km
Mon Dec 14 2009 13:53:49 's