I have taken the trip to northern Finland,
to Lemmenjoki National Park.
An area that's unknown to most
Norwegians, but interesting for me.
Not least because it's such a
large area. 2850 square kilometers.
I backpack
and pack my dog, Foss.
We will carry with us
all we need for a month.
Lemmenjoki is divided into two zones.
One's designed for tourism,
the other is nature untouched.
There are bonfire pits and tents
and marked trails.
Here you can experience
lots of nice scenery in a short time.
Because at only a few places
can you light a fire, -
- without wrestling with the wood.
It's waiting. Firewood.
So you can get to the good boutiques.
This is an exciting way
to organize a national park.
Most of the traffic is controlled in
a small area, the rest is untouched.
It's so wild I want to experience it.
You have to orient yourself.
The fishing is probably much better.
Thus it's tempting
for wilderness afficionados like me.
One can pack everything one needs
for a month. Know the bag -
- but it's livable. To achieve this
there are some things to think about.
One thing that increases the weight
of the bag for many, is the tent.
My tent weighs 1.1 kg. There are no
rods or stakes to set up.
But it keeps the mosquitoes
and the rain outside.
During the summer, and in the forest
you need nothing more than this.
So I have a nylon cover.
The first thing I do when I get
to camp, is to set it up.
Another advantage is that you can put things
out under the tarpaulin.
A sleeping pad weighs 0.5-1 kg.
The cheapest kind weighs 150 g, .
Sleeping bag weighs 700 g.
It's down.
Not particularly warm, but it doesn't
need to be in the middle of summer.
I have saved 5.6 kg by choosing the right
tent, sleeping bag and sleeping pad.
Here at Ravadasjärvi it's
comfortable and deserted. Beautiful terrain.
Mountainous terrain and woodland
complement each other.
That narrows it.
A nice trout, I'm sure.
I use live bait.
Knew it was over then.
It stopped swimming. So
I gave it 1-2 m, and let it sink.
Fifth or sixth time I
let spinners sink, I took it.
This is a nice trout.
I should be careful.
Not a gram off a kilo.
Is it possible to have it better?
Driving big trout, the smell of
birch-fire in the nose, nice and warm.
I'll take my time. It's in such
moments the rest of the world disappears.
This is the answer to why we do
it. Look at the wonderful fish!
Getting tired now.
Two rounds in the pot
to be done with it.
What a lovely fish.
Sitting in one corner.
Look at it, then!
In this small lake.
It's fun to think.
I have with me an electronic scale.
The range is accurate.
It stops at 1705 gram.
Absolutely beautiful fish.
It's more than I can eat
today. I'll eat half.
The other I will dig down into the marsh.
It's pretty cool there.
I'll eat it tomorrow.
He likes to be scratched
behind the ear more than Foss.
Check out these hills.
10-12 peaks
up to 600 m.
Beautiful terrain.
Hi! Morning, you.
Now I'll walk over the mountains.
Be back soon.
It's the nature of Lemmenjoki
that draws me here.
But this is also gold mining country -
rather special in Scandinavia.
I shall meet one of the gold miners.
Hello. Is it Mullius?
Hey, it's Lars.
The adventure started in Finnish Lapland
in 1868. They found 600 kg of gold.
Many of the largest lumps
are found in Lemmenjoki.
-Does not matter if it rains?
-Bad weather always come from Norway.
Yes, I agree on that.
Mullis would not
use motorized transport.
He goes in with backpack, sled.
Carrying material for the heavy way.
He will stay in shape
and operate on the basic level.
He can pan week after week, until he
takes the cream job: to wash & clean the gold.
It's what drives him.
-Not for large lumps anyway.
-Do you see any gold at all?
Now comes the most
exciting part of the job.
The last sands are delicate,
and then the gold appears.
-Sure nothing falls out?
-Yes. Gold is quite heavy.
-Here is something.
-Good. Lots of gold.
It's very smooth.
But we are not so deep down in the earth.
There's more there.
It bodes well
when you get even deeper.
But some can rejoice even more.
The eighth largest lump found in Lapland,
was found in the neighboring field.
That party we will not forget.
Was it you who did it? Congratulations.
And so it was you? Congratulations.
-Pekka.
-Risto.
-Thanks.
Is it possible to see that beautiful
nugget? Do you have it in your pocket?
Can I get hold of it?
Okay, thanks, bye!
He's from Norway.
The celebration takes place
at the Finnish goldmining show.
Cheers!
Thanks for now.
Continued success. Bye.
Fun party. Now we set our
heading for the deepest, -
- most secluded wilderness here.
In there, almost untravelled.
Talking about being in their own world.
This is a dream camp.
On the brink of a moraine,
with sandy bottom and light moss.
Close by the pond.
Soon I'll try the fishing rod there.
So we have Vaskojoki a couple hundred
meters down the road. And completely alone.
We went straight to an eagle's nest.
It's rare. And inhabited as such.
Probably golden eagle.
They are quiet when approaching.
But we heard it from a distance,
so there are no chicks in the nest yet.
Out walking at night?
What have you done with your mom?
Can't hang out on the corner here.
Think we'll send you off.
You can run to your mother.
I'm not your mother.
We'll begin to move
when you get rested a little.
Maybe your mother calls more for you.
I must get up.
Let's walk 100 m into the forest with you.
Bet that your mother finds you.
starting to eat.
Now we have gone almost twenty kilometers.
I have arrived at Vaskolompolo.
Here there's a hut.
Tomorrow an old
companion of mine visits.
Now we'll see
whether there are fish in the water.
Now I lie in a hut. And here it's
possible more anglers will come.
Then I should not let it fly what
worked well, on the fishing pole.
I have to put on something really bad.
When the other fishermen ask what I
hook grayling on, I'll show them that.
So keep
your secrets to yourself.
Morn. In the evening we can
be tempted with boiled grayling.
A kilogram and a half of cleaned fish.
Trond Strømdahl and I
have known each other since 1985.
A better man to have with one
in the field is hard to find.
-Good to see you.
-Been in long?
Seven or eight hours.
Taken at night to help.
It's a Lemmenjoki record.
I have something I think you will like.
Since you look a little sad,
a bit slim, I brought a little bacon.
Litt.
Then it grayling for you
and bacon for me.
-Are there trout you have caught with it?
-Harr. A lot of nice grayling.
Out there? Certainly fun, there.
Is "stupid" on my forehead, too?
-No getting grayling with that.
-Yes, it's an excellent grayling bait.
Fine, you think that. But your lure does not.
It has not had grayling on it.
There are some who know
me better than others ...
Fair that pike took it
when the grayling would not.
40 years ago, there was coffee in it,
North Marka. It was me and my dad.
Now it's with me on tour.
Thanks to my dad and all parents
taking with their young out in the woods.
There he sits, right in the country.
It's huge.
-See the log, then.
-Proper log.
It's larger than the two I have.
Kilo and a half at any rate.
By far the largest grayling I have
had in some time. It's an adult.
All the wilderness gods,
thanks that I get to experience this.
-I let it go a bit.
-You can, safely.
-It may be called grayling chief.
-The boss is in the water.
See the dorsal fin.
See the old man.
I'll check if it sits.
Holy damn! See the grayling.
We're talking log grayling.
Personal minimum before
was 750 g from Ljørdalen.
-Ljørdalen, goodbye.
-Here is the weight.
-This is my eager one.
-You guess 1.6?
It was 1.5.
This was worth the postal route miles.
(Speaking rapid Finnish.)
Lemmenjoki has been an adventure.
Damn shame to leave such a nice area.
We have walked through
true untouched wilderness.
The terrain has been very varied.
Pine and birch forest on top of each other.
All camp fires, camp sites ...
This tour has left some track.
One thing I can say with certainty:
Lemmenjoki - here I shall return.
(next week)
Finland is a paradise
for canoers.
Another pike follow
for it on the hook.
Better watch out.
He bites.
(English subtitles: Lex Ein)
(lexein-subs at yahoo dot com)
Sun Dec 06 2009 01:15:29 mil-km