I'm going to realize a dream
I've had for a long time:
Living one year in "Nordkalotten", above the
arctic circle of Norway, Sweden & Finland.
Seeking out the most unknown
parts of this wilderness.
Be there when the seasons change.
Travel the whole time. Fish. Hunt.
Experience animals at close range.
That's what really matters to me.
Say goodbye...
A quick kiss...
Good trip...
Thanks...
It's autumn...
During the next month I'll backpack from
Kalmankaltio in Finland to Karasjok.
I'm going to spend a lot of time in
Upper Anarjohka National Park.
It's one of the least known wilderness
areas, but also the most interesting.
During the trip I will meet a Sami moose
hunting party and stay with them a few days.
The rest of the time I'll be all
alone, just me and my canoe.
Since I'm starting on the Finnish side,
I'll have to carry a lot at first.
The reward is that I get to see parts of
Anarjohka few other people have seen.
I've walked a few km on a moraine by this river,
now I'm below where it meets another river.
And I come up on this ridge,
to lookout over the world!
Here, it's great!
I'll put my equipment here by the river,
and get rest for tomorrow.
It will be great to get my shoes off.
One of the extras I carry is a
pair of sneakers as camp shoes.
The little extra weight is worth it.
These boots are waterproof, but that
doesn't help when no water gets out, -
- so these socks are
drenched with sweat.
They are getting greenish.
This smells nice!
Now the pike stay in the pot
and enjoy themselves a bit.
I chose neoprene boots
instead of leather.
Because I will mostly be in the canoe, but
expected heavy lifting the first few days.
I have to say - for that job,
they didn't work.
My feet are really beaten up.
Last night I laid there two hours
feeling the pain in my feet.
It just hurt and hurt - the support
and sole are not good enough.
These don't work if you carry
more than 30 kilos.
For that, use traditional leather boots.
That's the price I pay
for bad footwear.
I chose the wrong boots.
This is just like a dream!
At the top of the waterway, it's crowded.
Hopefully there's more room downstream.
Right or left side in this rapid?
We just go down the middle...
Come on...
That's it...
So great!
We get paid for our toil!
Look at this!
This is what I want -
- to be alone in the wilderness.
Not many get to experience this.
I know how incredibly privileged I am.
I think about that every day.
No doubt this trout is at least one kilo!
Oi!
- that didn't stay put.
The first trout!
Dinner is secured!
You have no idea how great
that trout tastes.
When I eat pike and greyling,
I'm thankful for the food.
But when I eat trout, I'm thankful -
- that I'm not eating greyling and pike!
Here we have a cup of coffee.
It's a good comrade.
Typical spread; liver paté and cheese,
and cheese and liver paté...
Here's kit for the next fire. For the
next camp in case in there's no willow there.
Willow's great for starting a fire. Here is
coffee, two hunter's stews and mashed potatoes.
This is my residence. It's a bit small, I think.
The tent's under this tarpaulin to keep it dry.
I have enough guy lines to tie to the trees.
I hang my clothes under it, hopefully
near the fire so they can dry.
Moose hunting in Upper Anarjohka National Park
is exotic, and I can't wait to experience it.
I'll meet the hunting party at a cabin at Noarvvas.
At this speed I'll arrive tomorrow afternoon, -
- probably before they land by helicopter.
They are flying in.
Look at this,
these are moose footprints.
This is great moose country, but I haven't seen any.
I've just seen tracks, fresh spoor.
They are masters at staying away. Even one
man with no dogs in a canoe makes too much noise.
They sneak away.
But they're here...
I'll put up my tent here, even though it's
just 30 metres away from the hut.
It's better to sleep
with fresh air and no snoring.
-Hello! John Isaac.
-Nice!
Hi!
-Anne Risten.
Hi! Øystein Flage.
Josef Iver.
-Welcome to Noarvvas! Harald Ingebrigtsen.
-Thank you!
Hi! So nice you are!
You're great!
Upper Anarjohka is a national park, -
- and to avoid wear and tear,
hunters must be flown in.
So there will be a helicopter.
This is not a disadvantage if
you want extra provisions!
There are a lot of goodies.
-Home-baked bread and stuff!
-We're on vacation, so we're on vacation.
Lars, have a seat.
Here's some moose we shot last year.
-Fried and smoked in the Sami way.
-It looks fantastically good.
-Where should I sit?
-Here is a seat for you.
-Next to the old man.
-'Old man', are you?
He's younger than me,
but I call him the old man.
-Lapin Kulta.
-This will taste great! Thanks a lot!
Oi, oi ...
Fantastic morning.
Everyone is waking up and fast.
Not a breath of wind.
It's gray.
You can see moose a bit
better than when it's sunny.
Great Hunter in the group
is no doubt Anne Risten.
Despite the fact that she is only 18
years old, she has shot three moose.
Who takes a little more time,
is Harald Ingebrigtsen.
My name's Harald Ingebrigtsen
and I come from the Big Korsnes.
I've hunted for seven years,
and have not myself shot a moose, -
- but have been involved in
trapping a lot of moose.
Moose hunting is more difficult
in the Upper Anarjohka than many other places.
The terrain here is pretty flat.
Moose have no
narrow canyons or valleys to run in.
Therefore, hunting shapes up differently.
Using binoculars to a great extent.
One scouts for hours
until you find the animals, -
- and then sneak up on one.
Exactly where he,
in a way, controls us.
Now we can use the small gray
dog to get the better of him.
If we go over there with the dog,
we get safely far from them.
Now we are approaching the mound
where John Isaac saw the moose.
Øystein spotted another,
so there are two beasts there.
The dog is now off the grounds.
It could spook the moose to disappear.
I'll follow whoever I think will
shoot the moose. I'll walk with Anne.
Moose is about 400 meters away.
Behind the nearest small forest grove.
One cannot fool them twice.
-How far do you think it is there?
-How far is it?
300 meters.
It is exciting
getting this close to the animals.
Very thrilling.
There go the animals.
They were spooked.
They ran.
That's it. It was impressive
that we got video, anyways.
Now it's been six days of hunting.
We have been near moose
several times, but they were startled.
It is difficult
to approach them.
Hunting has given
little benefit in terms of reach, -
- but now we try a new method.
We will be laid out at night
in the middle of moose terrain.
Then we hope one comes to us tomorrow.
I grew up in a time of few
moose, so I have plenty of patience.
(gunshot)
I have to laugh.
This is day nine of moose hunting.
In the morning both John
Isaac and the dog slept -
- and the moose disappeared and was lost.
Then a moose cow shows up at the hut, -
- where Harald and Josef Iver are.
Harald's making coffee,
Joseph Iver's sitting on the toilet.
So Harald goes out and shoots the moose.
And our group
can only trudge back to the hut.
Congratulations!
-Who was the shooter?
-He's squatting down there.
-Congratulations, Harald!
-I just saw!
An evil tongue said
that Harald was totally scared.
It's been ten years
since you've shot.
It's only seven years, and I have
been involved in killing of moose.
We work as a team,
it's no good just to be selfish.
This time it was my turn.
So I couldn't refuse to shoot!
-It was funny that you got it!
So welcome!
Here is enough to enjoy.
We poor people have it good.
We show off our trophy!
Now the job's done.
-Congratulations!
-Thank you!
It was time.
I think you've grown!
What proof is this here?
Can we call it a felling drink?
-So you begrudge me that?
-We must treat you to it.
Should it all be drunk at once?
Then I must draw a breath.
Good as painful death!
20th of September.
First snow.
-See you!
-Have a good trip!
This has been a
very pleasant stay.
A fantastic nice bunch.
Fine nights with great
fun around the table.
Moose were here also.
Perfect.
But now I have to set
course for Bavttajohka.
I can bear it, -
- for I'll get a fantastic trip
through the heart of the wilds here.
It'll take ten or twelve
days to Karasjok.
First fire using pine.
The sight of the pines that
stand on the hilltop here, -
- was a delight.
Seeing the pines does something to one.
Then the good fire.
It's quite different
than a fire with birch wood.
Bavttajohka and the Anarjohka
are best known for white fish.
There have been a lot of grayling
in the past.
But if you go a little away from the river,
one can find good trout water.
Have you seen such a wonderful fish!
It's beautiful!
A magnificent example of trout.
I will just land it.
Wonderful!
Dinner is secured.
It is certainly red, and fine in the flesh.
I choose not to tell
where this water is flowing.
If too many are caught here,
the whole trout strain could disappear.
Look at the lovely shape.
It's a log!
It's unbelievable!
I'm standing just three meters away.
A kilogram trout is in the process
of digging a pit to spawn.
It goes in circles, just
like a dog going to bed.
And then curls its tail.
Amazing to watch!
It is so wonderful that
I lose the desire to catch them.
I have dinner for today and tomorrow.
I am pleased with that.
(learn to filet fish at nrk.no/monsen)
This tour through Anarjohka
has been a wilderness adventure.
In the morning I paddled
the last bit down to Karasjok.
Thus, the end of
paddling for the year.
At the same time, it's delightful
to think that this is just the beginning.
Winter is just around the corner.
The snow comes, the ice makes its bed.
It is a different world.
I can't wait!
There is only
one thing that remains.
Burning my underpants.
They burn well!
(next week)
Is there anybody home?
That was a huge wolf!
(Subtitles: Lex Ein, Sondre Paulsen)
(subs.hopto.org)
Sat Dec 05 2009 08:14:23 +toil,trophy