16. October.
I am in Pasvik with Foss, -
- A 13 month old Alaskan Husky.
Pasvik is bear country.
I'll meet one of the principal
experts on bears in Scandinavia.
Perhaps we'll also see
some exciting tracks.
What's this?
Interesting. Claw marks on trees.
Looks like a hollow lie.
Nice place to camp.
Do you hear something, boy?
No one is better qualified to talk
about these bear tracks -
- than Steinar Wikan from Pasvik.
Professional about bear tracks.
Good day.
Saw some effects on the environment?
Yes, clawing or biting.
Outstanding!
One of Wikan's projects is
collecting DNA material.
With that he has proven travel
patterns of 49 bears in Pasvikdalen.
I located where this bear has been.
In the bear pit.
You show real joy when you
come to a place with bear tracks?
Oh yeah, there are frequently quite
ordinary things. Manure, bites, etc.
But when you get such a collection,
nesting space, bites and filth, -
- And perhaps other trace materials,
you get a lot of DNA material.
And you learn a little about bear behavior.
Why have they bitten the trees in the middle
in the summer? Hardly territory marking.
Maybe he was just bored? He
must do something while he is here.
Many thoughts about bear behavior.
And how do bears think?
- For regular walkers - which
situations can be dangerous?
The most dangerous is
a wounded bear.
A shot or wounded bear
it quite dangerous.
All of the other dangerous situations
are a bit less dangerous.
One other is females with cubs.
We have many such cases.
Sometimes the bears
when confronted are scared.
But we have cases where they
have attacked. Then there are cases -
- where someone has a dog with them, which
has pursued a bear at its heels.
We have a few such cases,
where the bear has shown aggression, -
- but without attacking someone.
It was great to meet you.
Continued success on your
journey in our forests.
Pasvikdalen is 100-120 kilometers long
and 10-20 kilometers wide.
There's chance of
coming into a bear's presence.
We will start in the north
and go down south walking.
Much of the fun is that we should
be out in October-November.
That keeps most people indoors.
This is a real tour.
I am not here just to chase kilometers.
I'm here to relax and enjoy
the outdoors as I like to.
To go as far as we feel every day.
Might be staying in the same
place three or four days.
Maybe I'll take a trip
with the gun, fishing rod ...
Foss and I are here to enjoy ourselves.
But is it smart to walk at this time
of year? Should I have skis? Snowshoes?
Will much snow fall?
Wise people say there's usually
little snow before Christmas in Pasvik.
When I choose to trust them.
The question is whether I will happen
upon a bear. They aren't hibernating yet.
There are plenty who are out walking.
Good boy.
You must come when I call you.
This snowfall is very nice
When it comes to indicating tracks.
But it's a bit scary that
it covers over rockpiles.
It makes it a little hairy.
Have to be careful in the broken rocks.
There are a lot of those in Pasvik.
Satan in hell!
That's what I meant by not quite
seeing where you put your feet.
Good boy.
Such a good boy!
Is it a good idea to trim his claws?
Oh no.
When it's this cold and clear,
I lie there. Fall asleep by the fire.
Now comes the evening.
20. October.
Last night the ice was not safe.
In the night, it was
nine degrees below zero.
Then I ventured out on the ice
for the first time in years.
(crack)
Don't think I'm going to go far out.
Content myself with water.
It's mine.
Rice porridge is the king in the morning.
Have it Christmas Eve morning.
Of course, it has cinnamon, butter
and a little sugar. Then we are in heaven.
So it was you who stole my fish?
Then there's soup
for supper today also.
This is a perfect way to create
a strong bond with your dog.
I selected Foss because he shows
good characteristics for a tracking dog.
I can really get
into his head, -
- we connect very well.
Further on I'll make
him dog in my sled team.
And it's valuable to have a dog
as a guard in the camp.
When there are things around, he hears it.
If a rabbit jumps by -
- maybe it ensures dinner.
Reindeer can trample through.
And he's funny.
He's 13 months, young and playful.
A softwood block or log is enough
to get him in a good mood.
Here we come up to water.
It's hard to go on in this terrain.
Tempting to try the ice keeps.
It's worth a try. It will certainly
carry Foss with his claws. But me?
It's incredibly easier to walk on ice
than to flounder in the terrain up and down.
Even though one proceeds with cautious
steps, it's much faster.
The stone pile is huge.
Come on. It's much easier on the ice.
Down on the ice.
Come, then, boy.
It's important to not help him when
he tries. He must learn for himself.
Otherwise, he will stop all the time
and expect me to help him.
Good boy!
Here we go.
It is better.
A wonderful place to be a hiker.
A night in the open.
Check out the northern lights, hear the fire
crackling. Next night, We spend in there.
Western Hut is one of seven open huts
which is located in Pasvikdalen.
Open to all who want them.
A fantastic offer for hikers.
Indeed, it's just a plain resort.
I just had to out and get some air.
I will be here today. Accomplish
things that are hard to do -
- living in tents or out in the heather.
Is there anyone home here?
Bad set, maybe?
Great to have such things in nature. Provides
an extra dimension to the wandering life, -
- having bears around.
The probability that there is a den
within 10 kilometers from here -
- with a live bear in it, is great.
Fantastic to have it like that.
The first thing I do when I have picked
a camp, is to stoke the fire.
Delicious smells. That's when you get
up to the camp, then you need fire.
When you're usually a little cold and sweaty.
Then just bring up the flames.
These are some of the perks
of being in the pine woods.
In the initial phase, only throw on wood,
so there is a glowing layer the bottom.
There is open water below the marsh edge,
even if it's minus 14-15.
We go on a cold enough night for a meeting.
Make sure the lid is back by the fire,
so I do not lose it in powder.
When the fire is lit and the water collected,
it's time to put up the tent.
Then comes the evening.
It's important to slow down,
let your body be a little sluggish.
Don't hustle and fuss. It's okay
that things are going in low gear now.
It important to appreciate the
things you have. A bonfire,  food ...
Now that it's 40 cold, there aren't a
million mosquitoes, the storm's not blowing.
No, life is easy.
(learn to pack dog packs on nrk.no/monsen)
Although it has been cold,
I keep close to land.
There can be thin ice anywhere.
Not bad to arrive at
Ellen Cabin before it got dark.
Only fox and marten tracks on the path,
so it is deserted enough.
Of all the open huts in Pasvik
Ellen's Hut is the most visited.
It's easily accessible, and near
Lake Ellen, which is good for fishing.
And fine water for
paddling in the summer.
There, the sun peeped out.
Was sunny today, too.
Fun you can have with that, too.
Today I walked on Coal Mountain,
260 meters above sea level, -
- the national park's highest point.
Indeed, it's the weekend, -
- but I'm alone, even at the most
trafficked site in the Upper Pasvik.
Because I'm here in November,
I have all this for myself.
Inconceivable, if you ask me.
Something broke some branches there. We're
at the Finnish border, heading south.
It may have been a moose or reindeer.
I doubt that it was something else.
It continues to crack back there.
There are no moose.
So it must be a reindeer.
It can be a bear,
but it seems too cautious.
It was a huge wolf!
Completely black. Anyway very dark.
It heard us, and then took off
over there about 80 meters.
The dog is very excited.
Too bad I didn't manage to get it on tape.
Fun to catch a glimpse of the matter.
In the back laboratory.
So I measure out a yard.
We have the foremost laboratory.
It was a real surprise.
Must be running along the oil line
over the marsh.
That's a lot of signs.
When the clock is 11 in Norway, it's
12 in Finland and 13 in Russia.
Nowhere else in
the world is like that.
30 days go quickly
when you're feeling fine.
Being here when the snow falls, and
forest is white for the first time -
- feeling the silence, solitude,
days have become increasingly shorter ...
The Dark Age is just around the corner.
We will be touring throughout the winter.
I felt a lump
of joy in my stomach.
(next week)
The cold is like a lid over the country -
a closet. Been sacked by Santa Claus?
Rumor is that he has switched
to dogs. Is it not Santa Claus?
(English subtitles: Lex Ein)
(subs.hopto.org)
Sat Dec 05 2009 09:01:08  it's