It's Easter, 8 April. I am in Lappoluobal
with the annual deer relocation.
Antti Lantto and his wife Sara Kristine
will lead the way to the South Island.
It's a unique opportunity for me to
to experience reindeer herding up close.
The Sami have been doing
deer moving for hundreds of years.
It's the livelihoods of many here.
But they also compete.
Who has the fastest reindeer?
Of such things are made world championships.
-Would you show me a deer?
-Yes. There it is.
-It's long in the legs.
-It is very long in the legs.
And a long body.
A very good skater.
-That's your joke?
-We'll see tomorrow.
-Your grin hides an idea ...?
-I have expectations for it.
42.4. That's good.
Now there are only 200 meters left.
Tired. 1:24.3.
It was bad.
I'm not disappointed.
We'll be back next year.
Now they gather more owners'
reindeer in a fence.
Then they separate them, so they
get their own animals -
- then move them towards the coast.
No one's using a lasso.
We have a small are there.
We are running 40-50 animals in the throws.
So we pull them out.
It's much easier than the lasso.
Tom Arild Isaksen will also
be with the deer moving.
He knows what this is about.
And I, yes.
Now Sara Kristine and Antti separated
all the deer.
Now we can start moving.
I am looking forward to this trip.
We have ten days to go
200 km. The feed will determine the pace.
At Kvenvik waits a boat which will
take them to the South Island and summer grazing.
This is the first time I've awakened
with a snowmobile outside the tent.
But now I'm with the Sami people at their
premises to see deer moving.
It's no ordinary visit.
I may have with me what I want, but
keep it at a level I feel comfortable with.
Such as my one-man tent.
I could sleep in their big tent,
but to have a private life ...
I sleep very well in
small tents. They're like home.
The Reindeer are spread out, but they
have full control of where the animals are.
-What are you looking for when you camp?
-Location.
That we have control over certain
areas. Will the flock remain, -
- so we can see snowmobiles
and hear the bells.
Then we can go out and see
if we see the crowd.
I also run around the whole herd
and see if an animal has gone astray.
It may. But now it's such good
pasture that they hardly leave each other.
-How long are we here?
-Two days. At least.
My name is Sara Kristine Eira Lantto.
Reindeer herding is in my blood.
I was born and raised
in a reindeer-herding family.
Girls in a herding family don't have
the first right to run deer.
It was not the intention
that I should take over Dad's operation.
I was lucky to meet Antti.
Now we have our herd instincts.
It's useless to ask the Sami
how many deer are on a plateau ...?
It's like asking you how
much money you have in the bank.
I'll never answer.
You'll never answer me.
To move the reindeer herd over the mountain
may seem quite natural for the Sami.
But fewer and fewer do it that way.
Most people choose trailers.
Many animals are weak after the winter.
And moving costs more energy.
If we do not fit the tempo so that
they have enough food, someone will fall.
It's a delicate balancing act.
I and sleds are not good. Here I'll
just wait for someone to drop by.
It was deep there.
-I did well for low speed.
Over-like slush, minimum gas.
Then you float.
But this goes well.
Oh, thanks!
Moving and biscuits are great.
When I was little
and came here with my papa, -
- I learned to watch the stones,
mountains and the stars at night.
So you know roughly where you are.
Did you notice the stone we drove
past in place? A large stone?
Next time you drive past there,
you'll know which direction you should go.
-You don't use a compass?
-No. It's up in the head.
-What about GPS?
-I had one once.
I used it a few times to make
track. But you know where you are.
I sold it as fast as
I bought it.
Our relocation is
on pure animal premises.
And it's a good crowd at night, moving
us at night. And then we add the hay.
Thus we can determine
how far the animals will go.
It's the fourth day in the mountains.
So far, there has been great weather.
Now I did not have to take morning coffee
before there was a real wind.
Convulsions of King Winter. They
tend not to last more than a day.
Hearing what the plans are for the day.
-What do the animals do when it blows?
-Nothing, really.
If there is plenty of grazing.
Are you sure it's a dog?
-Yes. It's disturbing 1/4 of the herd.
If you gather the herd,
I'll go after the dog.
A strange dog
has got herself into the crowd.
Stray dogs are a problem in Kautokeino.
One has come in and bothers the herd.
Now they must do something about it.
Females who are pregnant,
may abort. That must be avoided.
Yes, but I don't own the dog.
I'm driving the herd south.
The sheriff asked you release the dogs.
If they chase after animals again-
- should you shoot them?
-It was what the police said.
It's very bad that they do not
come and pick them up.
Tom Arild is taking the dogs down to
the parish, so we don't have to kill them.
We're glad,
but the owner is more so.
Fascinating to see
how the animals find their way themselves.
They knew they were going up the slope.
Antti turned off the snowmobile engine.
Prefers not to push them too hard.
You enjoying yourself now?
-Yeah, it's good.
-Reindeer moving is a high point for you?
-Yes. It's really fun.
-Why?
-It's probably natural for us.
In spring, warm air, sunshine, moving reindeer.
What's better than that? Nothing.
-Secret Water? What's the name?
-I can not tell.
Secret Water is the secret of water.
This is the weapon.
Just a hook and maggot.
-The first one's free.
-Thank you.
Dog food.
It's just not great down here.
Now that's fish.
Now we throw a lasso
and see who is the best.
Family and friends have come to
help with the rest of the move.
And then join in with
a camp championship in lasso throwing.
Shoes laced and thoroughly warmed up.
Psyching out his opponents in advance.
Now begins the competition.
Five throws each and no cheating.
Nils Isak begins.
Camp Championship Winner: Mickey-Per?
Number Two: Antti.  And Number Three: Lars.
-Comment?
-Very nice of you.
-Your own efforts?
-Very poor.
(learn to throw a lasso at nrk.no/monsen)
We're all pretty tired, so we shall take the
the sled over the mountain, we shall.
-I was back in the crowd the whole time.
-One should not say the name of the mountain?
The elder folk say never to mention
the mountain when you're on it.
-But now we hope it goes well.
-Why should one not say the name?
I don't know. They say it's bad weather
if you talk about the mountain.
You can almost smell the sea.
One of the highlights during the move.
It smells like the deer, too.
They put on more speed.
Which carries them straight to the South Island.
The boat belonged formerly to the
Norwegian Ministry of Defence.
Now it runs shuttle service
between the mainland and islands.
Very many reindeer herders
along the coast use this boat.
Titanic.
-I'll be back.
-Feeling happy now?
-They all have been injury-free.
-Excellent.
Perfect relocation.
It's not possible to get better.
South Island is Norway's fourth largest island,
a fantastic place for reindeer.
Large areas to move about, safe
calving areas, few natural enemies.
It warms the heart.
They happily flock here for the summer.
In the autumn they will return
back to the mainland.
But that's "years on", as they say.
Now approaching the herd calving
area. They have gone straight for it.
-It was good they arrived.
-Yes, now they are at the calving site.
-It seems that there is bare ground.
-Which is great for calving.
Now you can begin calving.
Now we have arrived.
(next week)
Lars Monsen. Do you hear me?
Might not be completely safe here.
(English subtitles: Lex Ein)
(lexein-subs at yahoo dot com)
Sat Dec 05 2009 19:39:50