Okay, so I'm here today to answer
all of you guys' questions
and the first main question
that you guys have been asking me is:
what am I going to do now
that the conservatorship is over with?
Very good question.
Well, let's see I've been in
the conservatorship for 13 years.
It's a really long time
to be in a situation you don't want to be in.
Um, so, I'm just grateful honestly for each day
and being able to have, um,
the keys to my car
and being able to be independent
and feel like a woman
and, um, owning an ATM card,
seeing cash for the first time,
being able to buy candles.
It's the little things for us women,
but it makes a huge difference
and, um, I'm grateful for that.
You know, it's nice.
It's really nice, um,
but I'm not here to be a victim.
Um, I lived with victims my whole life as a child.
That's why I got out of my house
and I worked for 20 years
and worked my ass off.
I'm here to be advocate for people
with real disabilities
and real illnesses.
Um, I'm a very strong woman,
so I can only imagine, um,
what the system has done to those people.
So hopefully my little story—
Hopefully my story will make an impact.
So, um, make some changes, um,
in the corrupt system.
And the #FreeBritney movement, you guys rock.
Honestly my voice was muted
and threatened for so long
and, um, I wasn't able to speak up
or say anything
and, um, because of you guys in the awareness
of kind of knowing what was going on
and delivering that news to the public
for so long you gave it awareness,
um, to all of them
and, um, because of you,
I honestly think you guys
saved my life in a way, 100%.
Um, and I know there's a lot of jokes
about the #FreeBritney movement:
um, "we're not free, we're expensive."
Okay birdies, I'm expensive too,
but anyways, with that said:
um, let's move forward.
God bless you all.
We're gonna have a good year,
good Christmas
and rock on.